W.P.A. California Folk Music Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
W.P.A. California Folk Music Project collection 1936-1991 1938-1940
AFC 1940/001
United States. Work Projects Administration (Calif.), sponsor
Cowell, Sidney Robertson, 1903-1995, collector
7 boxes 4.5 linear feet.
manuscripts: 115 folders.
239 sound discs (35 hours): analog, 78 rpm, mono.; 12 in.
170 photographic prints: black and white; various sizes.
24 drawings.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The California Folk Music Project of the California Work Projects Administration (WPA) was conceived and directed by Sidney Robertson Cowell and co-sponsored by the Music Department of the University of California, Berkeley, and the Music Division, Library of Congress from 1938 to 1940. Additional support was provided by the New Music Society of California and the Society of California Pioneers. The resulting collection of sound recordings, photographs, correspondence, field notes, and drawings documents the musical culture, including religious music and folk song, of many ethnic and English-language performers in northern California. The collection includes the documentation of the music of Anglo Americans, Armenians, Assyrians, Basques, Croatians, English, Finns, Hungarians, Icelanders, Italians, Norwegians, Russian Molokans, Scots, Portuguese, Mexicans, Puerto Ricans, Spaniards and Spanish Americans from 1938 to 1940. The sound recordings were deposited in the Archive of American Folk Song at the Library of Congress in 1940. The collection also includes a few instantaneous sound discs made by Sidney Robertson Cowell in Missouri and Iowa for the Farm Security Administration in 1936-1937, and includes folk music research, writing, photographs, and technical drawings and sketches of the musical instruments, generated by Cowell and by the WPA staff who worked for her, plus related documents to 1991.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Acosta, Rosalie; Aslanian, Jack; Asmussen, Ella; Avila, Albert; Avila, Alice Lemos; Baboyan, Reuben J.; Bakalian, Jack; Bardarson, Leo; Bardarson, Otto; Bardarson, Sigurd; Barr, Alex, 1910-1978; Bateman, John (Photographer); Bedrosian, Joe; Bell, Sam (Folksinger); Benonys, Sigridur; Blackburn, Sam; Boro, Peter; Botica, John; Botkin, Benjamin Albert, 1901-1975--Correspondence.; Brady, Hubert; Brangone, Louis; Brodeur, Arthur Gilchrist, 1888-1971; Brown, Hilda Duarte; Calderón, Aurora, 1909-2006; Coffin, Ada Pearl; Coffin, Byron H.; Coffin, Byron, Jr.; Cook, Charles (Fiddler); Cowell, Henry, 1897-1965--Correspondence.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson, 1903-1995; Cowell, Sidney Robertson, 1903-1995--Correspondence.; Cowell, Sidney Robertson, 1903-1995--Ethnomusicological collections.; Cunha, Frank; Cunha, John; Cunningham, John (Singer); Daniels, Joe (Musician); Daniels, Joe (Musician); Day, William T.; De Soto, Jessie; De Soto, Tomas; Dedo, Tony; Denoon, R. R., -1971; Dormody, Anita; Dornbush, Adrian--Correspondence.; Drasky, Mary; Earnson, Flora; Edgar, Marjorie, 1889-1960--Corresondence.; Einarsson, Thordur; Elkus, Albert I. (Albert Israel), 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Emrich, Duncan, 1908-1977--Correspondence.; Erro, Antoinette; Espinosa, Lottie; Etcheverry, Frances; Etcheverry, Matias; Fetesoff, William S.; Figueroa, Ben; Flores, Joaquim; Flores, Olive; Ford, Arthur J.; Ford, Bogue; Ford, Elizabeth W.; Ford, Pat; Ford, Warde H.; Franco, Clifford; Franco, Louise; Franks, Mr.; Fulton, Charles (Pianist); Gaidos, Mary; Garcia, Johnnie; Garcia, Maria (Singer); Gomez, Julio (Musician); Goshtigian, Hartop; Goshtigian, Mary; Gould, Hattie Scott; Graham, George Vinton; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961--Correspondence.; Hall, J. L.; Halpert, Herbert, 1911-2000--Correspondence.; Handon, Joseph H.; Haroutunian, Bedros; Harp, Walter; Hart, Harmon; Herzog, George, 1901-1983--Correspondence.; Hobrecht, Bertrand; Jabbour, Alan--Correspondence.; Jelenfy, Elizabeth; Jelenfy, Mr.; Jones, Leonard W.; Kendall, Raymond, 1910-1980; Koljonen, C. A.; Koljonen, Celia; Korson, Rae--Correspondence.; Kratlian, Archie; Lemos, Manuel; Lindsay, Bennie; Lindsay, Junior; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002--Correspondence.; Lomax, John A. (John Avery), 1867-1948--Correspondence.; Loscutoff, William S.; Lozada, Cruz; Lucido, Sal; MacInnes, Charlotte; MacInnes, Donald; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982--Correspondence.; MacPhee, John; MacPhee, Mary; Madariaga, Mrs.; Mann, Thomas B.; McCready, John A.; McCready, Spencer; McDonald, Mary A.; McKenzie, Leighton; Meade, Virginia; Medeiros, Antonio; Mendes, Alberto (Musician); Morgan, Aaron, 1861-1942; Myers, Evarista; Nilssen, Alf; Nimerfroh, Mr.; Nimerfroh, Rosa; Olafson, John; Olmeda, Mario; Oriet, Frenchy; Ortega, Jacinta; Pavon, Ed; Petersen, Fina; Pico, Virginia; Pitts, Ben; Ponce, Leon; Popoff, Mr.; Popoff, Mrs.; Powell, Charles (Guitarist); Ralph, Walter Ross; Rasmussen, Charles (Judge); Reha, Julia; Rice, Ben, 1872-; Robinson, Leighton; Rodriguez, Elinor; Russo, Joseph W.; Ruthling, Pablo; Salonen, Mary; Sanfilippo, Francisco; Sanford, Herbert Hudson; Sanoff, J. D.; Sarakoff, A. P.; Schetinin, William T.; Sebree, Walter; Seeger, Charles, 1886-1979--Correspondence.; Selleck, John N.; Shapazian, Siranoosh; Shapazian, Vartan S.; Sharp, James B.--Correspondence.; Shatinian, T.; Sigurasson, Oddrun; Silva, Elzira; Silveira, Mary; Soininen, John; Spivacke, Harold, 1904-1977--Correspondence.; Stone, John E., -1952; Susoeff, J. P.; Susoeff, J. P., Mrs.; Takakjian, Mesrob; Walker, Robert W., 1883-1961; Waters, Ozzie (Water witcher); Wilbur, Ray L. (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949--Correspondence.; Wilkinson, Myrtle B.
Organizations
Archive of American Folk Song; Aslanian's Armenian Orchestra; Julio Gomez' Orchestra; Library of Congress. National Digital Library Program.; New Music Society of California.; Society of California Pioneers.; St. Anthony's Seminary (Santa Barbara, Calif.). Choristers; St. Joseph's Seminary (Santa Barbara, Calif.). Boys Choir; Stanford University. Choir; United States. Work Projects Administration (Calif.); University of California, Berkeley. Department of Music; W.P.A. California Folk Music Project Collection, 1938-1940 (Library of Congress)
Subjects
Alabados.; Armenian Americans--California--Music.; Ballads, English--California.; Ballads--California.; Basque Americans--California--Music.; Bawdy songs--California.; British Americans--California--Music.; Carols--California.; Children's songs--California.; Courtship--Songs and music.; Croatian Americans--California--Music.; Dance music--California.; Fados--California.; Fiddle tunes--California.; Field recordings--California.; Finnish Americans--California--Music.; Folk dance music--California.; Folk music--California.; Folk songs, Armenian--California.; Folk songs, Basque--California.; Folk songs, Croatian--California.; Folk songs, English--California.; Folk songs, English--California.; Folk songs, Finnish--California.; Folk songs, Hungarian--California.; Folk songs, Icelandic--California.; Folk songs, Italian--California.; Folk songs, Norwegian--California.; Folk songs, Portuguese--Azores.; Folk songs, Portuguese--California.; Folk songs, Scots--California.; Folk songs, Scottish Gaelic--California.; Folk songs, Spanish--California.; Folk songs, Spanish--Mexico.; Folk songs, Spanish--Puerto Rico.; Folk songs--California.; Georgian Americans--California--Music.; Gold miners--Songs and music.; Humorous songs--California.; Hungarian Americans--California--Music.; Hymns--California.; Icelandic Americans--California--Music.; Immigrants--California--Songs and music.; Italian Americans--California--Music.; Loggers--Songs and music.; Love songs--California.; Lullabies--California.; Medicine shows--California.; Mexican Americans--California--Music.; Minstrel music--California.; Molokans--California--San Francisco--Music.; Musical instruments--California.; Norwegian Americans--California--Music.; Political ballads and songs--California.; Polkas--California.; Popular music--California.; Portuguese Americans--California--Music.; Puerto Ricans--California--Music.; Ragtime music--California.; Rímur.; Scottish Americans--California--Music.; Sea songs--California.; Sermons, Russian--California--San Francisco.; Singing games--California.; Spanish Americans--California--Music.
Places
California--Music.; California--Songs and music.
Titles
California gold, northern California folk music from the thirties.; W.P.A. California Folk Music Project collection, 1938-1940
Form/Genre
Drawings.; Ethnography.; Field notes.; Photographic prints.; Sound recordings.
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts, II. Sound Recordings, III. Graphic Images.
Acquisition
Sidney Robertson Cowell; Gift; 1940.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
Inventory of the California Folk Music Project records, 1938-1942; Music Library, University of California, Berkeley: http://oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf9s200870 >
Sidney Robertson Cowell collection, 901-1992; Music Division, Library of Congress: http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.music/eadmus.mu010010
Sidney Robertson Cowell correspondence, 1936-1973; Music Division, Library of Congress. (ML94.C69)
Access and Restrictions
Access restrictions apply. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Online Content
A substantial portion of the collection, with interpretive essays, is available as "California Gold: Northern California Folk Music from the Thirties," http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000002
Biographical Note
1903 Born Sidney William Hawkins in San Francisco, California on June 02
1924 B.A., Romance Languages, Stanford University, Palo Alto, California Married Kenneth Robertson (divorced 1933)
1935 Henry Street Settlement
1936 Music assistant to Charles Seeger, KL Division, Music Unit, Special Skills Division, Resettlement Administration (RA). Accompanied Frank C. Brown and John A. Lomax on recording trip to western North Carolina where she received training in using a portable sound recording machine and assisted in recording Anglo American melismatic singing and African American singing in chain gang camps for the RA. Travelled on her own to collect traditional English-language music in Arkansas, Maryland, Missouri, South Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia for the RA.
1937 Regional representative, Special Skills Division, Resettlement Administration. Collected recordings in Minnesota and northern Wisconsin (including Warde Ford and his extended family, many of whom moved to California to work in the CCC camps at the Shasta Dam where they were recorded by Robertson for this WPA collection). Community relief community manager, Special Skills Division, Resettlement Administration. Recorded Finnish, Serbian, and Gaelic performers; recorded Swedish, Lithuanian, Norwegian, and Finnish performers at the 4th National Folk Festival held in Chicago, recorded lumberjacks in Michigan.
Late 1937 Traveled to Washington, D.C. and California to explore plans for developing and funding folk song collecting projects through New Deal arts organizations and private grants organizations. Began to do folk music research in her native California.
Early 1938 Received endorsement from the Music Division at the Library of Congress and 200 blank acetate discs for recording folk music in California, under the provision that the Library's Archive of American Folk Song receive copies of the original field recordings she made. She also received approval from the Department of Music at the University of California, Berkeley, for co-sponsorship for their support in providing office space.
Late 1938 Through the sponsorship of the Library of Congress and the University of California, Berkeley, Robertson was able to apply for and receive WPA (Work Projects Administration) approval for her California Folk Music Project through the Berkeley office of the Northern District of the WPA in California. As such, she received help from twenty persons on the labor relief rolls. The CFMP opened officially on October 28, 1938.
1940 The CFMP was brought to a close, due to a lack of the renewal of WPA funds, which were intended to allow for the collection of Asian and Middle Eastern folk music in California during an additional two years. During this year, she compiled and published The Gold Rush Song Book with Eleanora Black.
1941 Married Henry Cowell and began to use her married name, Sidney Robertson Cowell.
1942 Published The Bibliography of American Folk-Song and Folklore with Alan Lomax.
1950 With Maud Karpeles, traveled during the fall to seek out and re-record singers and their families who had performed for Cecil Sharp in Appalachia in 1916-1917.
1953 Recorded American Folk Music Concert, Columbia University, at the 6th Annual Festival of Contemporary American Music; bagpipe tunes and Scottish Gaelic singing on Cape Breton Island, Nova Scotia; Spanish and Persian singing in Alameda and Berkeley, California; and the Shady [New York] Methodist Church Choir.
1955 56 Traveled for fourteen months to Europe and Asia, recording in the Aran Islands, Ireland in June 1955, and again in June 1956. Included travel to record traditional music in Iran, Thailand, Pakistan, and Malaysia.
1995 Died February 23 at her home in Shady, New York.
Administrative History
The California Folk Music Project (1938-1940) was the result of a joint effort of the Northern California Work Projects Administration, the Library of Congress, and the Department of Music at the University of California, Berkeley. The project was officially sponsored by the University of California at Berkeley and co-sponsored by the Library of Congress. The New Music Society and the Society of California Pioneers offered their support and encouragement for the collecting project. The effort also received some funding from the California State Relief Agency.
Prior to the California Folk Music Project, during 1936 and the early part of 1937, Sidney Robertson had collected traditional English- and foreign-language music for the Special Skills Division (KL) of the Resettlement Administration (RA). When the Resettlement Administration was liquidated late in 1937, and with it, Robertson's source of funds for recording, she looked for means to continue and expand the scope of her folk music collecting in her native California under the auspices of the WPA.
Robertson was eager to organize and conduct ethnographic and folk musical research on a nationwide basis in order to engage in more comprehensive field collecting than was being done at the time. She discussed her plans with Luther Evans, then Librarian of Congress and an old friend from Stanford University, who suggested that the WPA in California might be willing to fund her project. The WPA contacts Robertson made through Evans became convinced that such an undertaking might best be initiated on a state-by-state basis. Robertson was promised WPA funding for a prototype of her collecting plan in any single state, providing she could get the necessary 50% contribution for the equipment, supplies, and rent required for government projects of this kind. With such support, she was expected to devise work that could keep from twenty to forty people employed from the work relief rolls and also be acceptable to at least three sponsors. Robertson chose to pursue the project in California, where she sought sponsorship for it through the University of California at Berkeley late in 1937.
It was in the Department of Music at the University of California, Berkeley, under the chairmanship of Albert Elkus, that Robertson found a willing sponsor for her folk music collecting plans in California. With Elkus' help, Robertson's project received university support for space and equipment. And, because she conceived her collecting project as being of relevance to the fields of anthropology, history, sociology, literature, and ethnology, Robertson made contacts with interested faculty members in a variety of university departments, who offered her their support. With the University of California as an official sponsor, Robertson was then eligible to apply for WPA funds to hire personnel to assist her in the task of collecting and documenting traditional music in northern California.
Once WPA sponsorship of the project was established, the Archive of American Folk Song at the Library of Congress, then under the Music Division's leadership of Harold Spivacke, agreed to co-sponsor it by providing 12-inch acetate discs for recording the music and offering cataloging assistance to organize the collection. For additional non-labor items, which the WPA did not cover, such as catalog cards and travel expenses, the project received financial support from the California State Relief Agency. In addition to the backing of official project sponsors, Robertson sought assistance and support for it from other academic sources. As an advisor on ethnographic standards for conducting fieldwork, the anthropologist Paul Radin offered guidelines that could be applied to the collecting of folk music. From George Herzog, Columbia University ethnomusicologist, Robertson received suggestions on techniques for the melodic analysis of folk music. Through Herzog's support, she developed a project that accorded importance, not only to preserving the texts of folk songs, but also to collecting traditional melodies and their variants so that they could later be analyzed musicologically. A duplicate set of recordings on disc were given to the University of California, Berkeley, for the purpose of establishing the Archive of California Folk Music in 1940.
Although the Archive of California Folk Music was never established, the recordings became part of the Music Library of the University of California, Berkeley and in the early 1980s, they were put on permanent deposit in the Stanford University Archives of Recorded Sound. The Music Library at the University of California, Berkeley, also retained copies of administrative documents, English translations on folk music, material on music in the California missions, lists of California songsters and hymnals, song texts with references to California, material on Portuguese, Spanish and Latin American folk songs, and sketches, scale drawings, and tracings of folk instruments.
Scope and Content
The California Folk Music Project of the California Work Projects Administration (WPA) was conceived and directed by Sidney Robertson Cowell and co-sponsored by the Music Department of the University of California, Berkeley, and the Music Division, Library of Congress from 1938 to 1940. Additional support was provided by the New Music Society of California and the Society of California Pioneers. The resulting collection of sound recordings, photographs, correspondence, field notes, and drawings documents the musical culture, including religious music and folk song, of many ethnic and English-language performers in northern California. The collection includes the documentation of the music of Anglo Americans, Armenians, Assyrians, Basques, Croatians, English, Finns, Hungarians, Icelanders, Italians, Norwegians, Russian Molokans, Scots, Portuguese, Mexicans, Puerto Ricans, Spaniards and Spanish Americans from 1938 to 1940. The sound recordings were deposited in the Archive of American Folk Song at the Library of Congress in 1940. The collection also includes a few copies of instantaneous sound discs made by Sidney Robertson Cowell in Missouri and Iowa for the Farm Security Administration in 1936-1937, and includes folk music research, writing, photographs, and technical drawings and sketches of the musical instruments, generated by Cowell and by the WPA staff who worked for her, plus related documents to 1991.
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Finding Aid (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Subseries I: Correspondence 1937-1958; 1980-1991
      Subseries I contains correspondence materials that represent the pre-WPA period which spans September 21, 1938-October 20, 1938. During November 1938-February 1940 and post-WPA April 1940-September 1958.
      - Correspondence, Pre-WPA Project, September 21, 1937-February 1938 (Box-folder 1/2)
        Correspondence to and from Robertson, memoranda, project proposals, and other materials relating to pre-California Folk Music Project activities and queries. Correspondents include Henry Cowell, Adrian Dornbush, Albert I. Elkus, Herbert Halpert, George Herzog, Alan Lomax, John A. Lomax, Charles Seeger, James B. Sharp, Harold Spivacke, the Society of California Pioneers and others.
      - Correspondence, Pre-WPA Project, March 1938-May 1938 (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Correspondence, Pre-WPA Project, June 1938 -October 1938 (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Correspondence. November 1938-July 1939 (During WPA project) (Box-folder 1/5)
        Correspondence to and from Robertson, memoranda, reports, and other materials relating to the California Folk Music Project while the project was being funded. Correspondents include Percy Grainger, George Herzog, Alan Lomax, Charles Seeger, Harold Spivacke and others.
      - Correspondence. August 1939-February 1940 (During WPA project) (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Correspondence. April 1940-September 1958 (Post-WPA project) (Box-folder 1/7)
        Correspondence to and from Sidney Robertson (after 1941, Sidney Robertson Cowell), memoranda, reports, and miscellaneous materials relating to the California Folk Music Project once it had been discontinued. Includes information about intended follow-up projects planned in the 1950s, material of folkloric and ethnomusicological value relating to the music already recorded, and plans for reviving the WPA-like cooperation of funds and resources through a consortium of universities, archival institutions, and collectors. Correspondents include Benjamin Botkin, Albert I. Elkus, Duncan Emrich, Percy Grainger, George Herzog, Rae Korson, Alan Lomax, John A. Lomax, Harold Spivacke and others.
      - Correspondence. August 1980-April 1991 (American Folklife Center) (Box-folder 1/8)
        Correspondence between Sidney Robertson Cowell and the American Folklife Center relating to Library of Congress' interest in making the California Folk Music Project Collection accessible to the public online. The folder also includes some Cowell reminiscences about the WPA project. Correspondents include Alan Jabbour and others.
    - Subseries II: Administrative Materials related to California WPA Project
      - Grant proposals and statements of purpose (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Forms and background materials prepared for WPA project workers by Sidney Robertson (Box-folder 1/10)
        "Instruction to workers for the Collection of Traditional Music in California." Forms to be used in conducting fieldwork on the project. Bibliographic key word list Guide for WPA workers responding to "General Queries." Bibliography.
      - WPA progress reports (Box-folder 1/11)
        Report dated July 20, 1939, and another for the period from October 28, 1938 to September, 19, 1939, both prepared for the Northern California WPA Office.
      - Final Report of UC-Berkeley Faculty Sponsors (Box-folder 2/12)
        Statement of sponsorship for the WPA California Folk Music Project by faculty of the University of California, Berkeley, February 14, 1940.
      - Final Report of the California Folk Music Project Submitted to WPA (Box-folder 2/13)